Hello English learners, welcome back to another edition
here with us at English Pod, my name is Marco and I'm Erica
and today we are doing the third part of our old English
series and today we're transported back to the 1970s.
That's right, so we're going to learn
some 1970s slang some phrases that
were really popular back in the
70s but are also still in use today.
Exactly, so it's going to be a very cool lesson
today and before we start with the dialogue,
let's take a look at some of the words that
we're going to find in vocabulary preview.
vocabulary preview.
Well, we have two words
for you in vocabulary
preview and they're both
found in the dialogue.
The first one, roller rink.
A roller rink.
Okay, so a roller rink, let's break that
down and let's look at the first part.
So roller, we might recognize this
from roller blades or roller skates.
Okay, so yeah, when you
go to rollerblading, roller
skating, those things that
you put on your feet to skate.
Right, wheels, not like a blade or a knife.
Exactly, so that's roller
and what about rink?
rink is the place where you do skating.
Okay, so if you go to
a roller rink, it's this big
area where everyone can
rollerblade or roller skate.
That's right.
Okay, and what about the next word?
A block.
Okay, so this is a noun, a block.
And a block is a part of a city
that is surrounded by four streets.
Okay, so a city is made up of many
blocks and everyone lives on a block.
Exactly, so it's a square within the city.
All right, very good, so these
are the two words that we
previewed and we're going to
listen to them now in the dialogue.
We're going to hear two guys
just talking about normal everyday
things, but we're going to
be listening to them in 1970.
Hey man, how's it hanging?
Hey man, everything is just groovy, baby.
Did you go to the roller rink on Saturday?
I heard it was far out, man.
I wanted to, but I ran into this foxy
lady that just moved to my block.
I was chatting her
up a bit and then we
mellowed out at her
plate right on, right on.
Well, Jim went to the rink with
Sherry and he said it was done.
No mites.
He was low on bread, but
Sherry paid for everything.
gravy! Jim is such a jive turkey, man.
He's always hitting me up for cash.
Anyway, you want a book
and go grab some grub.
Yeah man, I'm starving.
Okay, groovy dialogue.
Yeah, really nice, huh?
All right, so some
interesting language in here.
And like I said, it sounds
a bit strange, but a
lot of this is still used
today in modern English.
So why don't we look at some of
these words in language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
All right, on language takeaway
today, we have the first word, far out.
Far out.
That was far out.
To be far out.
Okay, so it's just another
way of saying cool.
Cool, that was nice.
Yeah.
It was really cool.
So they went to the roller rink.
It was far out.
It was really cool, but the other guy
couldn't go because he saw a foxy lady.
A foxy lady.
Okay, foxy lady.
So basically a foxy lady is a
really good looking or sexy woman.
Right, commonly you would hear some
men refer to a attractive woman as a fox.
Okay, so foxy lady.
Now, Marco, can we say a foxy man?
No, this is a phrase that you
would only use for women.
Okay, so foxy lady.
Foxy lady.
So after he met up with the foxy lady,
they both just decided
to mellow out at her place.
To mellow out.
Okay, so mellow out.
What does this mean exactly?
Basically, just to relax.
Right, so to relax to
take it easy to mellow out.
So what did you do on the weekend?
Oh, nothing.
I just stayed at home and mellowed out.
Okay.
All right.
And so the response to that was
right on, right on, right on, right on.
Right, right on, right on.
And so basically they're
saying, okay, good.
I agree.
Yeah, this phrase, you can say as good.
Yeah, that's nice or you can
also say it as well, correct, correct.
I agree.
So why don't we listen
to some examples of
how we can use this
word in other situations.
Example one.
Right on.
You got a high score.
That's amazing.
Example two.
You got the job right on.
Example three.
Jenny was right when she told me
she thought Rick was no good for me.
I should have listened to her.
Okay, so I think that's pretty clear.
We can see how it means
correct or also, okay, good.
All right, right on.
And now we also have another
word that's similar to far out.
He said gravy.
Gravy.
Now, if you look it up in a dictionary,
it's going to tell you something else.
Gravy is a sauce you put on meat.
Right.
But in this case, we say gravy is cool.
It's nice.
Yep.
Right.
So gravy.
That was gravy.
Now, finally, at the end of their
conversation, they said, want a book.
Okay, let's book.
Book.
So two book is a verb.
Yeah, interesting verb.
It basically means to
leave a place quickly.
Okay, so we have to book.
The police are coming.
Right.
Or I got a book, guys.
It's going to be late.
So book to leave quickly to leave suddenly.
Yep.
And that word is used quite
commonly today, isn't it?
Yeah, yeah.
It's used among like younger people.
You would say, yeah, let's book.
This party is dead.
Okay, great.
So there's a lot of pretty
cool phrases in this dialogue.
Pretty groovy phrases.
Why don't we hear them again in context?
Hey, man.
How's it hanging?
Hey, everything is just groovy, baby.
Did you go to the roller rink on Saturday?
I heard it was far out, man.
I wanted to, but I ran into this foxy
lady that just moved to my block.
I was chatting her up a bit, and
then we mellowed out at her place.
Right on, right on.
Well, Jim went to the rink with
Sherry, and he said it was dot no mat.
He was low on bread, but
Sherry paid for everything.
Gravy.
Jim is such a jive turkey, man.
He's always hitting me up for cash.
Anyway, you want a book
and go grab some grub.
Yeah, man.
I'm starving.
All right, so now that
we understand these
six words that we saw
in language take away,
it's time for us now to
take a look at some great
phrases that we can use
today in fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
Okay, so at the start of the
conversation, there was an
interesting way he started
talking to his friend, right?
All right, he said, how's it hanging?
How's it hanging?
Okay, so basically, how is it going?
How's it going?
How are you?
Now, you notice in the spelling that
we do have a G at the end, I and G, right?
Yeah, but usually you
don't really pronounce the
G in this context
because it's very informal.
So how's it hanging?
How's it hanging?
So he said everything was
just groovy and then he started
telling him about how he met
a girl and he chat her up a bit.
Shh, to chat her up.
Okay, so to chat somebody up.
So when you chat someone
up, you talk with them, right?
Yeah, you're making conversation.
But it's sort of, it's more
than just conversation, isn't it?
Yeah, you're trying to be
a little bit flirty and maybe
saying nice romantic
phrases or something like that.
Yeah, so usually it's between
a woman and a man, right?
And it's the man who chats up the woman.
Yeah, exactly.
So a little bit of a
sexist phrase here to
chat someone up or
to chat up a girl, right?
Okay, so he was chatting her up.
That's right.
And so they were talking
about how Jim went to the
roller rink, but he didn't
have any money, right?
Because Jim is always
hitting his friends up for cash.
Okay, so to hit someone
up, to hit someone up.
So before we explain this word,
let's listen to some other examples.
So then we can maybe
understand the meaning.
Example one.
Can you believe Patrick,
he came up to me a
month ago and tried to
hit me up for some money?
Example two.
When I was a kid, I used to always
hit my dad up for lunch money.
Example three.
This is the last time I lend you money.
Don't even try to hit me up for more.
All right, so when you hit someone
up for something, you ask for it.
So usually it's to ask for money, right?
Okay, so to hit someone up.
And now for our last phrase, let's
book and let's go grab some grub.
To grab some grub.
Grab some grub.
Okay, let's break this one down.
With the final word, grub,
what are we talking about?
Grub is an informal way of saying food.
Okay, so to grab some grub
is to get some food quickly.
Yeah, let's go get some food.
All right, so maybe it's time
for us to grab some grub.
And while we're doing that, you can
listen to the dialogue one last time.
Hey man, how's it hanging?
Hey man, everything is just groovy, baby.
Did you get the rollering considered it?
I heard it was far out, man.
I wanted to, but I ran into this foxy
lady that just moved to my block.
I was chatting her up a bit and then we
mellowed out at her play right on, right on.
Well, Jim went to the wrinkly Sherry
and he said it was done no mites.
He was low on bread, but
Sherry paid for everything.
gravy!
Jim is such a jive turkey, man.
He's always hitting me up for cash.
Anyway, you want a book
and go grab some grub?
Yeah man, I'm starving.
All right, so some interesting
phrases and even though some
of these words you may not
really commonly hear anymore,
they might still be using movies
or something that's related
to the disco era because it's
very, very popular still, right?
Yeah, that's right.
Some of our more advanced
users could even use a lot of these
phrases in a kind of funny
way to reference back to 1970.
Yeah, exactly, so it's fun
and well, you will use them
or you will hear them from
time to time, even today.
And remember, if you have any
questions about the language you
hear in these lessons, check out
our website at EnglishPod.com.
Exactly, we're there to answer any
questions and we'll see you guys there.
Thanks for listening and until next time.
Goodbye!